<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A reply to a scandalous pamphlet entituled A declaration against judicial astrology written by the quondam (most ignorant and weak) practitioner Mr. John Raunce. Wherein he is both stript of all his weak arguments, and confuted as altogether ignorant of the art. By William Ramsey gent qui est artium candidissimus amator.</title>
            <author>Ramesey, William, 1627-1675 or 6.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1650</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 33 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A57767</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R210</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R219039</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99830575</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99830575</idno>
            <idno type="VID">35028</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A57767)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 35028)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2076:07)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A reply to a scandalous pamphlet entituled A declaration against judicial astrology written by the quondam (most ignorant and weak) practitioner Mr. John Raunce. Wherein he is both stript of all his weak arguments, and confuted as altogether ignorant of the art. By William Ramsey gent qui est artium candidissimus amator.</title>
                  <author>Ramesey, William, 1627-1675 or 6.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for W. Larnar at the Black-moore in Bishops-gate-street,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1650.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A reply to: Raunce, John.  A brief declaration against judicial astrologie or, the diabolical art of astrologie opened, arraigned, and condemned.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Worcester College Library, Oxford.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Raunce, John, 17th cent. --  Brief declaration against judicial astrologie or, the diabolical art of astrologie opened, arraigned, and condemned --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Astrology --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:35028:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A REPLY TO A Scandalous Pamphlet ENTITULED A DECLARATION AGAINST Judicial Aſtrology, WRITTEN By the <hi>Quondam</hi> (moſt ignorant and weak) Practitioner Mr. JOHN RAUNCE. Wherein he is both ſtript of all his weak arguments, and confuted as altogether ignorant of the Art.</p>
            <p>By <hi>William Ramſey</hi> Gent. <hi>Qui eſt ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium Candidiſsimus amator.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ars non habet inimicum niſi ignorantem.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>W. Larnar</hi> at the <hi>Black-moore</hi> in <hi>Biſhops-gate-ſtreet,</hi> 1650.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:35028:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:35028:2"/>
            <head>A REPLY TO A Scandalous Pamphlet entituled, <hi>A Declaration againſt Judicial ASTROLOGY.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T hath been (and is commonly) known, that in all ages there hath been one or other that hath denyed, nay openly writ againſt the moſt manifeſt Truths, nay, even againſt the Divine Scriptures themſelves; being meerly either ſtirred up with a ſelf-conceited pride of their own knowledg, or envy that any ſhould profeſs or ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ntain for truth what they are altogether ignorant of. Amongſt which beaſts &amp; envious novices, I may juſtly &amp; lawfully reckon this Learned Mr. <hi>J. Raunce,</hi> who is ſo impudently audacious, to condemn what in the leaſt manner he can nether underſtand or comprehend, and that is the Art of <hi>Judicial Aſtrology;</hi> which he
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:35028:3"/>firſt begins to condemn, by opening the vanity of the Art, in it ſelf, (as he called it) which he ſaith, is <hi>a kind of Diabolical Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vination, Page</hi> 2. <hi>line</hi> 2. of his ſcandalous Paper; but how he can prove it Diabolical, more then by barely ſaying ſo, is as far beyond his wit to perform, as it is for him to apprehend the myſtery and verity of the ſame; and <hi>l.</hi> the 3 and fourth, he perſiſts in his vilifying malicious ſpeeches thus; <hi>being full of Idolatry and Superſtition, and is contrary to the Scriptures.</hi> And this he endeavours to prove thus, <hi>No man can Divine by the Stars, but by obſerving of time,</hi> and (ſaith he) <hi>this regarding of time is not lawful,</hi> as you may find <hi>Deut.</hi> 18. (<hi>ver.</hi> 10. ſure he means) for he names no verſe, as diſtruſting his underſtanding in the text, as well he may, if the words be throughly weighed and conſidered, which are theſe; <hi>Let none be found among you which is a regarder of times;</hi> This he picketh out of the midſt of the text, and from the midſt of nine ſeveral kinds of Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition, there rehearſed, affirming thus generally, that <hi>Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy</hi> is there comprehended; but I am confident all his ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low brains cannot prove, that <hi>Aſtrology</hi> is in the leaſt mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by name in thole words by him recited but if he had more particularly conſidered the text, and with a candid eye, he had never thus over-ſhot himſelf, and declared himſelf ſo appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently malicious to the Art of <hi>Aſtrology,</hi> to apply this text to ſignify <hi>Aſtrology;</hi> only becauſe it mentioneth the obſerving of time, for ſaith he, <hi>l.</hi> 11. <hi>p.</hi> the 2. <hi>it is well known unto us, that in divining by Stars which is Judicial Aſtrology, the Aſtrologer is not able to divine or foretell any thing, but by obſerving of times;</hi> which words he brings to prove, that by that paſſage of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is meant <hi>Aſtrology,</hi> which is meerly his own conſtruction; for, it will puzle both him, <hi>Perkins, Picus</hi> and all that ever durſt to bark enviouſly at the Art, to prove by Scripture, or ſhew therein any paſſage wherein God doth plainly forbid men, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Jews</hi> or <hi>Gentiles,</hi> to ſtudy the Art of <hi>Aſtrology,</hi> or prohibit indeed any knowledge of his Creatures, which is a good and probable means to bring us to the knowledge of his Divine ſelf; not to Idolize them as he would needs poſſeſs the vulgar, that <hi>Aſtrologers</hi> do; when <hi>Aſtrologers</hi> know and do confeſs
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:35028:3"/>they are but ſecondary cauſes, and ſigns of the will and pale ſure of God, inclining the diſpoſitions and humors in man, being compoſed of the 4 Elements; not compelling (as he would moſt erroneouſly and maliciouſly perſwade the vulgar) that Aſtrologers maintain. Wherefore except he could have proved that paſſage of Scripture to ſignifie Aſtrology by bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and ſounder arguments then his own, which is ſo weak and groundleſs, that it vaniſheth with himſelf, not fit either to be more mentioned or thought on; and yet this Idiot is ſo fantaſtically conceited of this his own bare conſtruction, and cenſure of the Scripture, that he thereon concludeth with himſelf, that his opinion and judgement he ſo readily pumpt out of his ſhallow Cocks-comb, is ſo invincible an argument, that he thus perſiſts, <hi>See here now what your Aſtrology is, is it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing elſe then Superſtition and Idolatry? For they ſay one time is good, another bad,</hi> and further thus, <hi>thus you may ſee that what the Scripture ſaith God made only good, they make to be both good and evil.</hi> By which argument he would fain conclude, Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy to be ſuperſtitious, as if a fatal neceſſity were concluded, which is not an opinion of the <hi>Aſtrologer,</hi> as I ſaid before, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do they make time both good and bad, for the worſt time as ſickneſſ and other caſualties, which perhaps he means the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrologers</hi> call bad times (for he declares not his mind, what he means, nor what he would be at) is good in ſome ſence, for it tends to the glory of God in one kind or other, how ill or bad ſoever it may appear to ſuch a Novice as him; for the world nor nought therein , had ever been made bur for his glory, ſo that the Scripture is no wiſe by the <hi>Aſtrologer</hi> contradicted, when he tells a man an ill time of trouble, or ſickneſſes, Cros<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, or the like, is ſuddenly to happen on him, he calls it per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps an ill time, as having relation to the patient or party, that muſt undergo theſe afflictions; yet this time in it ſelf brings perhaps this ſuffering wrath by afflictions to God and his fear, or perhaps brings death, however it tends to the glory of God, and therefore in it ſelf the time is good; <hi>Ergo</hi> no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction of the Scriptures by the <hi>Aſtrologers,</hi> in making that time which God made good, to be both good and ill.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:35028:4"/>
            <p>Again he perſiſts in his inveterate malice, and runs on with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out either fear or wit, not knowing indeed what he ſays, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo inveterately malicious, for he ſaith <hi>Aſtrology</hi> denyeth the providence of God in the diſpoſing of the ſeveral changes that happen to man in this life, (if ruled by the Stars) <hi>for ſay they</hi> (meaning the <hi>Aſtrologers</hi>) <hi>thus ſhall this man live and dye, becauſe of the Stars he had in his Nativity, and of another man, thus quite contrary, by reaſon of contrary poſitions of the Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ets at the Birth.</hi> I pray conſider, and you ſhall ſee this to be very wickedneſs, for God ſo ruleth the world by his providence that not a ſparrow falleth to the ground, nor a hair of our heads without his permiſſion; therefore (ſaith Mr. <hi>John Raunce</hi>) <hi>it muſt needs follow, that the whole courſe of our life is only governed by the providence of God alone, and not by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtellations of the Heaven.</hi> So that, by this argument he would fain conclude, and prove by thus cavelling, that the Stars were made for no uſe, but him and ſuch Idiots to gaze on; when as the Scripture in plain tearms tells us, they are for days and times and years. <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.14. but I would fain he would tell me, why the immediate providence of God is not ſhown to alter (from the courſe of the Moon) the ebbing and flowing of the Sea, nay the Thames here in <hi>England,</hi> that every Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terman can tell him the juſt time by the motion of the Moon? (for it may be he never ſaw the Sea.) I could mention and inſtance many more effects of the Planets, but perhaps they will ſeem Riddles to him, and Paradoxes, and ſo it may be will deny them, becauſe he is ignorant of them, as he doth the whole Art; but every common Water-man will convince him of this, if he have not brains either to conceive, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it; but to come cloſer home to the purpoſe. The in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence of the Stars on mans body, is ſo far from denying the providence of God, that it clearly proveth it to be the more manifeſt; for God worketh not immediatly, neither doth he cauſe rain, or ſnow, or froſt, or faire weather immediatly; but hath left the cauſe of all theſe to their influence, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the ſeveral aſpects and poſitions of the Planets, ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it ſo from the beginning; neither doth he work any new
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:35028:4"/>work, but what ever happeneth, was pre-ordained to come to paſs in its due time, ſo that he doth now no work, but ſits and upholdeth all by his Omnipotent, Omniſcient wiſdom and power: ſo that it adds to his glory, that when he made thoſe heavenly Bodys the Planets, to rule all ſublunary things and times, that he fore-knew the events, diſpoſitions of men, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terations of Kingdoms, Commotions, Plenties, Famines, Plagues, Healths, Sickneſſes, Wars, Peace, and what not by their effects; Neither let this ſeem ſtrange to Mr. <hi>John Raunce</hi> who is ſo well acquainted with the Scriptures, that he brings proof againſt what he underſtands not; for Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Come ye bleſſed of my Father, inherit the Kingdom prepared for you before the beginning of the world, Matt.</hi> 25.34. and <hi>Paul,</hi> to the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſians, chap.</hi> 1. <hi>v.</hi> 4. proves us to be predeſtinated and choſen before the beginning of the world; ſo that it is cleared, that what ever ſhall happen from the beginning of the world and before, to the end, was pre-ordained to happen: ſo that if a man by the poſition of the Planets at his birth be ordained to be (according to natural cauſes a theef, a murtherer, or the like) what can Mr. <hi>Raunce</hi> ſay; that will become of that man by this immediate providence of God, but deſtruction if God doth not mercifully ſhew his goodneſs towards him; this doth no wiſe certainly derogate from the providence of God, who hath ordained ſuch and ſuch accidents to happen to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man, from the beginning of his life to the end. He comes then with his inveterate malicious railings, (which becomes an Oyſter-wench far better then a Schollar, who ought to prove rather their arguments by reaſon and ſence, then envi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous names, without proofs, or indeed reaſon at all,) for ſaith he, <hi>And now for horary queſtions, what are they? are they any thing leſs then ſatanical deluſions, as is the veſt of that wicked Art?</hi> Certainly there is no judicial impartial eye, but will rather think him to be inclining to diabolical practices then <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrologers,</hi> and alſo ſo judge him, to belye ſo publick an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent truth as <hi>Aſtrology</hi> is, (as before I ſhut up my full diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe I ſhall ſatisfy him it is) to call it Diabolical and no wiſe prove it ſo, which is as falſe as all his frivolous arguments
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:35028:5"/>againſt it, and lyers are Diabolical I am confident, ſince the <hi>Devil</hi> is their Father, and the more Diabolical and apparently he ſhews himſelf to be the Child and Inſtrument of the <hi>Devil,</hi> by his envy, to rail in ſuch groſs tearms againſt truth, which his Father the <hi>Devil</hi> hath ever in all ages ſtrived to eclips, by ſuch ignorant inſtruments and Children of his, as <hi>John Raunce;</hi> and let him not be angry, if I ſhould here alſo call him dunce, ſince he tells me in his Title-page, he was ſometimes a practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioner of the Art, and is yet ſo ignorant as to call it Diaboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call; but indeed his weak ſhallow brains could no wiſe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or attain to the knowledge of it: a learned man or a wiſe man would rather have admired what he could not underſtand, then preſently to raile againſt it, and not able to prove it ſo, and this ſerves very fitly to prove him really a dunce, or at leaſt a fool to condemn what he underſtands not in the leaſt manner; for how can he prove this Art Diaboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, which depends only on the true and perfect knowledge of the Starres (that hath no affinity (I am confident he will ſay himſelf) with his Father the Devil) and their influences, which are but natural things; And by knowing natural and earthly things, <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, we ſhall know heavenly things the better, much more then by knowing the Stars, which are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove us, when the knowledge of what is beneath us, made <hi>Ariſtottle</hi> (that ſome time attributed all to nature) at laſt confeſs there muſt needs be a <hi>Deity</hi> and a <hi>God-head:</hi> and <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> ſaith, the <hi>Stars</hi> are ſignes; and <hi>David,</hi> The <hi>Heavens</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare the glory of God. Certainly, then no wiſe Diabolical yet this impudent, ignorant, envious dunce (who thinks his own words (he is ſo ſelf-conceited a fool) is ſufficient to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn an Art, and ſuch an one, as that his ſhallow Cox-comb can no wiſe obtain (which is the ground of his envy,) doth not ſtick to contradict him that tells us truly what the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens declare, and what the Stars ſignifie, (without any proof but his own word, which is as vain and empty as his brain, and too light by many ounces to prove his Argument, yet wants light to make a judicious impartial eye ſee that dark ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance whereof he dreams) and with it the Scripture;
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:35028:5"/>though he ſaith, <hi>ſhew me in what place of the Scripture the Art of Aſtrology is upheld or juſtified,</hi> when it will puzle all his learned brains, to ſhew me any one place (though he ſaith there are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and ſets ſome down, which I ſhall make clear to him do no wiſe ſerve for his purpoſe) that doth really condemn or diſallow of it; but he muſt know that the divine word was written wholly for our inſtruction to ſalvation, not to decide the legal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity or illegality of <hi>Aſtrology,</hi> or other Arts; yet what is above ſaid, is enough to any gallant ſpirit of the lawfulneſs of his ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and inſight therein, ſince they declare the glory of his Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor; I know not how then learned M. <hi>Raunce</hi> will prove it either Diabolical or illegal, or contrary to the Scripture, ſince it tends to ſo good an end, that the knowledge thereof is the declaring and manifeſting the glory, and greatneſs of the omnipotent Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator of both us and them; But to come to his proofs of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture he imagins condemns <hi>Aſtrology.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His firſt is, <hi>Deut.</hi> 18. his ſecond. <hi>Eſay</hi> 47. his third, <hi>Dan.</hi> 2. his fourth, <hi>Jer.</hi> 10. his fifth, <hi>Mich.</hi> 5. he tels you no particular <hi>ver.</hi> where in any of theſe places, you may readily turn to it: leſt then you ſhould diſcover his envious knavery in wreſting the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, but tells you at random the Chapters; that ſo you may ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther conclude as he ſaith, then deſire or ſeek to trouble your ſelf to diſprove him.</p>
            <p>Concerning his firſt proof <hi>Deut.</hi> 18. it is in the 10. <hi>v.</hi> though this proof be already anſwered him before; yet I will ſay thus much, that I am confident Mr. <hi>Raunce</hi> nor his author Mr. <hi>Perkins</hi> can prove, that in this place there is either <hi>Aſtrology</hi> or <hi>Aſtrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers</hi> named; I might therefore with as good liberty, and better reaſon, deny any ſuch matter, then he affirmeth it, for it is his part to prove, but let Mr. <hi>Raunce</hi> conſider the word in the ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal, <hi>gnonen,</hi> which our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Tranſlatours in this place take for a regarder of times; yet in other places otherwiſe, as in 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 33.6. the ſame word is taken for <hi>witchcraft,</hi> and in the 5. of <hi>Micha</hi> for <hi>Southſayers;</hi> wherefore I may ask Mr. <hi>Raunce,</hi> why not in this place of <hi>Deut.</hi> it may not as well be interpreted <hi>Witchcraft</hi> or <hi>Southſayer</hi> as well as <hi>a regarder of times?</hi> or elſe he muſt underſtand ſuch <hi>a regarder of times,</hi> as maketh his election by <hi>Witchcraft</hi> and <hi>Southſaying,</hi> and not by <hi>Aſtrology.</hi> But ſuppoſe
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:35028:6"/>we underſtand the word as the <hi>Engliſh</hi> tranſlate it, and as he would have, yet all obſervation of times is not forbidden, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by this place is the <hi>regarding of times</hi> by <hi>Aſtrology</hi> proved unlawful, or prohibited; for <hi>Solomon</hi> the wiſeſt of men ſaith, <hi>the heart of the wiſe knoweth time;</hi> and further, <hi>that there is a time for every thing, a time to plant, a time to pluck up, a time to be born, and a time to dye, a time to break down, and a time to build, a time to kill, and a time to heal, a time to weep , and a time to laugh, a time to mourn and a time to dance,</hi> &amp;c. to the 9. verſe, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 3.2.3.4. which none but the fool neglecteth: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if this were the true ſence of the word, all are prohibited to <hi>obſerve times</hi> in general, would not Mr. <hi>Raunce</hi> think it a ſtrange thing, or at leaſt that man to be as mad as himſelf that ſhould, when he ſhould ſleep, go walk abroad , or when he ſhould go about his buſineſs, go to bed and ſteep, or a man to weep when he ſhould be merry, and be merry when he ſhould mourn; or go to plough when he ſhould reap, and the like: wherefore we muſt take this place to ſpeak of the ſuperſtitious obſervation of times; but this learned <hi>Practitioner</hi> Mr. <hi>Raunce,</hi> in what he underſtands not, will needs intrude <hi>Aſtrology</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong witch craft and ſouth-ſaying, when all that knows any thing in <hi>Aſtrologie,</hi> will condemn him rather for a novice, then an <hi>Artiſt,</hi> ſince <hi>Aſtrologie</hi> hath not in the leaſt any relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the obſervation of any times but what are natural: wherefore this being a meer wreſt of the text, or at leaſt an ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant miſtake in learned Mr. <hi>Raunce.</hi> I hold it not conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent longer here to inſiſt, but leave him to peruſe for his better nodefication the 2. Chap. of Sir <hi>Chriſtopher Heydon,</hi> in defence of <hi>Aſtrologie,</hi> where he may have a full reſolution and confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of his former queſtion and proofs, he hath ſet down in his <hi>Pamphlet,</hi> or can in any other; wherefore I wholly refer him and all of his ſimple mind, to condemn any thing before they underſtand, to the ſerious peruſal of the ſame, and haſten to reply his remaining Cavils.</p>
            <p>His next is, That becauſe the drift of <hi>Aſtrology</hi> is to foretel of the particular events of things, he will not becauſe — but leaves it to all that are not drunk with <hi>Aſtrologie,</hi> to judge how
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:35028:6"/>contrary it is unto the Scripture. Truly Mr. <hi>Raunce,</hi> no more contrary unto it, nor the word of God, then you may think me your enemy, becauſe I ſigne your being a Scholler, and a learned man, a book of <hi>Hebrew</hi> or <hi>Greek</hi> to read, which per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps the vulgar underſtands not. Shall the vulgar ſay becauſe you can diſtinguiſh every Character and word, together with his ſignification and force that you are a <hi>Witch,</hi> or a <hi>Southſayer,</hi> meerly becauſe you paſſe them in knowledge and learning, and therefore you are (concluding without rime or reaſon) a <hi>Witch</hi> contrary both to God and his word? this is the reaſon why you ſay <hi>Aſtrologie</hi> is contrary to the word of God, becauſe in your weak apprehenſion you conclude they work by illegal means as <hi>Witches</hi> and <hi>Southſayers;</hi> but ſure it is ſo long ſince you were a <hi>Practitioner,</hi> (for you ſay <hi>ſome time a Practitioner</hi>) that I believe time hath rooted the rules of Art quite out of your memory, or it was ſo ſhort a time you practiced, that you did not fully attain unto them; but it had been your part to have proved it ſo.</p>
            <p>But Mr. <hi>Raunce,</hi> I pray what is a <hi>Comet?</hi> is it a natural Star, or a ſupernatural Signe? if a natural Star, why then is it not alwayes viſible? if a ſupernatural Signe, to whom doth God ſhew this Signe and wonder in the Heavens? ſure, nay I am confident, not to ſuch weak <hi>Practitioners</hi> as contemns the Art, as to be both diabolical &amp; contrary to the word of God; nor to the vulgar, that underſtands not in the leaſt what it may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern: therefore of neceſſity it muſt be ſhewen to the <hi>Aſtrologer,</hi> &amp; that to fore-warn the people of their puniſhment which is likely, (without ſpeedy and unfained repentance) aſſuredly to fall on them for their ſins: wherefore it is ſo far from being contrary to the word of God, that it agreeth therewith; for did not God allow both of the art and the ſtudy thereof, he would neither ſhew a ſigne by the Stars, nor particularly to <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrologers;</hi> for he might otherwiſe as well foretel and pread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſh a Nation by other ſignes and wonders, as by <hi>Comets</hi> and <hi>Blazing-ſtars.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:35028:7"/>
            <p>
               <hi>And now it is high time I ſay ſomething of the rules of Aſtrology, and then you ſhall ſee what it is, that is the foundation of Judicial Aſtrology.</hi> I think rather Mr. <hi>Raunce,</hi> it is high time for you to leave off cavelling with what you neither underſtand, nor can prove unlawful in the leaſt manner, or to go to ſchool to learn the foundation thereof, before you venter to ſpeak againſt it, when you cannot prove any thing you ſay, for your words are, <hi>Now then in ſhort, I ſay thus much,</hi> viz. <hi>that all the Rules and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts of Aſtrology ſet down by the wiſeſt men in that learning, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they were</hi> Chaldeans <hi>or</hi> Egyptians, <hi>or any other whatſoever; I ſay the rules of the ſaid Art, are nothing elſe, but meere dotages and fictions of the brain of man.</hi> And this is ſhort enough God knows, of what you would fain ſpeak if poſſible, &amp; ſo ſhort that if I ſhould meaſure it with your wit, it hath the full length ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; I thought a man of learning would have brought proofs ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by reaſon and Arguments of his own, or other bodies for what he writs againſt; and not to content himſelf with a plain <hi>dico,</hi> without either argument, proof or reaſon. <hi>In ſhort, I ſay thus much,</hi> viz. &amp;c. and again, <hi>I ſay the Rules and Precepts of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrology, &amp;c.</hi> But I ſay it is no matter what you ſay, or can ſay, or whether you ſay any thing or nothing, except it be to more purpoſe. You ſay, <hi>it is the fictions and dotages of mans brain;</hi> and I ſay, your brains are doted and beſotted; therefore let me have better reaſon then one Doctors opinion. I ſay more, how is the Art proved to be the fictions of mans brain a whit the more for your ſaying ſo? Where do you make it appear to be ſo? Or that their rules have no foundation in nature? we ſee that you have no foundation nor natural reaſon to condemn it; for we ſee nothing but your own words againſt it. Then I ſay, that you might even as well have ſaid nothing, and then you might have been ſtill thought wiſe; for <hi>ſtultus tacendo dicetur ſapiens,</hi> and then you might alſo have gone for a Practitioner; but now you have loſt your credit, both in the one and the other, for none but <hi>ſtulti</hi> will condemn a thing they underſtand not, nor can prove to be ſo; neither can any man practiſe any Art, but what he is vers'd in; but this cavil of Mr. <hi>Raunce</hi> his, is (I conceive) (ſince his doting brains cannot comprehend the true ground and reaſons of the Art) to learn them by writing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:35028:7"/>them, and ſo to receive inſtructions from the pen of the replyer; But I know no reaſon any one ſhould do him that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, ſince he is ſo openly malicious, nor is any one bound to prove the grounds thereof, except he could diſprove them, or know what they are: which ſince he is ignorant of, is ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to prove his cavil inconſiſtent either with reaſon or truth; His words are, <hi>And what are your houſes which are in number</hi> 12 <hi>what are they? and how cometh it to paſs they ſignify thus and thus? and what are thoſe many ſignifications that you give them? are they any thing elſe then very Fables and fictions of an old Idolaters brain? If it be not ſo let the Aſtrologers now ſtand up, and prove their Art.</hi> Stand up babes and ſucklings, and anſwer Mr. <hi>Raunce,</hi> which asketh if this be not ſo and ſo, and never proveth it ſo. Mr. <hi>Raunce,</hi> it had been your part in writing againſt this Art, to have given your reaſons and proofs, not your conceptions (which I know none are bound to anſwer) and then you had done Practitioner-like, and might perhaps have received an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer. Now Mr. <hi>Raunce</hi> cometh to write of the planetary An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, and as he ſaith, to tell you <hi>what they are.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The words of your Authors upon this matter are to this purpoſe,</hi> viz. <hi>That from the beginning of the world there were</hi> 7 <hi>ſperits ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed as rulers to the</hi> 7 <hi>Planets, and every one of theſe ſpirits ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth the world a certain time, &amp;c.</hi> all which is true, and I would very fain Mr. <hi>Raunce</hi> could in the leaſt diſprove it: all that he can ſay is this, <hi>Now theſe Planetary Angels what are they? are they any other Angels or ſpirits, then thoſe very wicked ſpirits, which are ſo often and moſt commonly, the chief agents for the imaginations, in their ſeveral operations and conjurations, as it is well known unto him that hath been a Profeſſor of Aſtrology, and Student in the Magick Art?</hi> I would very fain know how by theſe words Mr. <hi>Raunce</hi> proves or ſhews what the Planetary Angels are, as he ſaid he would, he tells us only what the Practitioners in <hi>Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy,</hi> and the Students in the Magick Art know them to be; he tells us nothing of his own knowledge, who knows as little in this, as in all his fore-going cavelling arguments; but it ſeems it is his way of arguing, to ask I pray what is this and that, is it not ſo and ſo? and is it not known, or it is known, by ſuch and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:35028:8"/>ſuch to be thus &amp; thus, never proving any thing, yet con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning every thing, meerly becauſe he is ignorant thereof<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> For otherwiſe certainly in his Arguments, eſpecially when it is his to prove and condemn, he would ſhew all his skill and ſtrongeſt reaſons if he have any; but as no body can anſwer till ſomewhat be propounded: ſo neither can nor will I prove what Mr. <hi>Raunce</hi> knows not, nor can diſalow of, <hi>Now ſeeing it is thus</hi> (then ſaith Mr. <hi>Raunce,</hi> as concluding upon no grounds of ſeaſons, neither any ſufficient proofs) we ſhall find <hi>Aſtrology,</hi> that is thought by many to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend upon the Stars, to have its being from no other thing nor ground then <hi>conjuration</hi> hath. If this be Mr. <hi>Raunce</hi> his reaſon, to conclude an argument without reaſon; I muſt conclude, it is like himſelf. And to argue with one void of reaſon, is to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der himſelf no whit better then ſenceleſs or mad; but as I ſaid befo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, he had done very well to have proved his cavils, that ſo he might have had an anſwer, and not to content himſelf with the bare ſaying, this is ſo, and ſo: without proof; which is not the part of a Scholar<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and ſuch an one as is to prove an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument; yet Mr. <hi>Raunce</hi> as great an enemy as he is to <hi>Aſtrology</hi> in his 4. <hi>page,</hi> towards the latter end, acknowledges the Predi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of <hi>Aſtrologers</hi> to be true; yet out of a pernicious envy would fain buze the vulgar, with a conceit (that he neither doth nor can prove,) that the Devil brings it to paſs; O ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious Mr. <hi>Raunce</hi> that meerly becauſe he is ignorant of <hi>Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy,</hi> ſhall without any proof or argument, condemn <hi>Aſtrology</hi> to be Diabolical; which opinion of his, is ſufficiently anſwered above, ſo that in this place needs no more, but to remember the reader, that he take notice of the envy and malice of the moſt learned Practitioner Mr. <hi>Raunce.</hi> And thus have you all his cavils ſet down to the full, and anſwered.</p>
            <p>For the concluſion of Mr. <hi>Raunce</hi> his diſcourſe, he makes a great profeſſion of zeal and holineſs, admoniſhing all good Chriſtians not to medle, or have to do with <hi>Aſtrology,</hi> (becauſe he cannot comprehend it) and tells them that he was raiſed up to gain-ſay, and withſtand that wicked Art. (but not to prove it ſo) I believe he is one of Mr <hi>Sedgwicks</hi> tribe (and many others <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> might name but for brevity ſake,) which was alſo raiſed up to forthtell the day of judgement, and to preach falſe Doctrine
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:35028:8"/>in ſheeps clothing; (crac'd-brain people) but I believe Maſter <hi>Raunces</hi> diſtemper, came meerly by too much practizing <hi>Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy,</hi> when he was a Practitioner in the ſame; And therefore like the Fox, who becauſe he could not attain to the full enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the ſweet Grapes he ſo earneſtly longed after, went a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, and concluded they were not ripe nor perfect: ſo Mr. <hi>Raunce</hi> becauſe he could not dive into the grounds and reaſons of the Art, (becauſe it was too high for his capacity) concluds it to be Diabolical and illegal, &amp;c. he ſaith, he knows that ſome will (as ſoon as his (learned) Declaration appears,) ſhew them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves of what ſpirit they are; for ſaith he, <hi>they will be amazed,</hi> and indeed well they may, to ſee his ignorance and envy; but eſpecially of him being a Practitioner, and yet ignorant of what he ſaith he ſometime practiced. But Mr. <hi>Raunce,</hi> let me adviſe you to practice hence forward ſilence, and Admiration of what you underſtand not, and make not your ſelf rediculous, envi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly to cavil and raile, (without either proof or reaſon) againſt any Art or thing you know not. And ſo I leave you to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, for I am heartily ſorry to ſee your ignorance, and weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, though you are unknown to me; for ignorance is the root of all evil, nay, and enemy to all Arts and Sciences; which is very unſeemly in any man that will profeſs himſelf to be any de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree above a Carter: much more in a Practitioner, in one of the moſt liberal Sciences at this time revealed to mortals. <hi>viz.</hi> Aſtrology.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Vale.</salute>
               <signed>Will. Ramſey.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Die ♂ 20. Auguſtii. 1650. Veſperi.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:35028:9"/>
            <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <p>I Would give Mr. <hi>Raunce</hi> here ſome Inſtructions in the Art, and prooſs to prove the myſtery thereof, to ſurpaſs his apprehenſion (as in ſome <hi>Patet</hi> already) as alſo to ſhew the verity and ſufficiency of the Art; for the better ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of the curious reader, as alſo of Mr. <hi>Raunce;</hi> but that I leave it to the Practitioners in the art, whom it far more concerns and belongs to; yet ſince for my recrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion I have had a little inſight therein, I could not for the well-wiſhes I owe to both the Art and Artiſts, but write what I here commit to the publick view; yet I make no queſtion but they will take him in hand, and put him hence forward to perpetual ſilence; for in all his ſcandalous Pamphlet he proves nothing, only runs on with an inve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terate, malicious, railing ſpeech, grounded meerly on his own ſhallow apprehenſion and conceit; wherefore, I leave it to their conſideration, to judge it their part or no to ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie their Art, not but that I would do it; but it would be better and more ſeemly for them that are Practitioners therein, ſince he openly challengeth them thereunto.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
